Vancouver Women in Trades fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Vancouver Women in Trades fonds
1976 - 1987
F-9
Q100144518
88 cm of textual records 4 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 4 photographs located in F-9-4-0-7
Vancouver Women in Trades
The Vancouver Women in Trades Association (VWITA) was formed in 1979 and incorporated under the British Columbia Societies Act in 1983. It became inactive in 1987. The organization functioned as an advocacy and support group for women working in, or seeking to work in trades and technology. It sought to facilitate contact among tradeswomen, improve their working conditions, promote greater representation of women in skilled, blue-collar occupations, and further women's access to trades education and training. In pursuing these goals, the Association frequently acted in liaison with other groups, government agencies, unions, businesses and educational institutions. The group also maintained links with other Women in Trades Associations across Canada, including the Women in Trades Kootenay Council. Membership in VWITA generally ranged between forty and fifty women. Annual general meetings and regular monthly meetings were forums for collective decision making, while a number of elected standing committees and coordinators initially carried out on-going business. In 1983 one paid staff position was created (Office Administrator) and in 1985 staff was expanded to three (Office Coordinator, Research Coordinator and Liaison Coordinator). These positions were primarily funded through government grants. Prior to the Association's incorporation in 1983, it was also known as the B.C. Women in Trades and the Women in Trades Association of B.C. Officers of the organizations included Joan Blair, Judy Doll, Alison Stewart, Carolyn Sawyer, Kate Braid, Suzanne Gerard, and Lynn Ryan.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the organization.
The fonds of the Vancouver Women in Trades Association consists of records created and received in the course of administering the organization and providing support and advocacy for women working in trades and technology in the Vancouver area. Activities documented include annual and monthly meetings; office administration and funding; liaison with other groups; advisory work on vocational curricula; outreach projects; and advocacy around specific issues. Document types include constitution, minutes, correspondence, logbooks, worksheets, policy statements, briefs, reports, speeches, questionnaires, and photographs and illustrations. The fonds also contains published reference material, whose publication dates in some instances precede the foundation of the Association itself.
Records were originally used and maintained by the Association as a single unit of office files. Series titles and arrangement have been supplied by the archivist in order to facilitate intellectual access to the documents. The arrangement was chosen to reflect activities falling under a similar function and generating related records. Nevertheless, overlap among groupings occurs, and the entire file list for the fonds should be reviewed to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject. Researchers should also be aware that strict chronological and alphabetical order was not originally maintained within files nor has it been supplied by the archivist.
Vancouver Status of Women; Braid, Kate; Gittens, Carlyal; Photographic materials; Textual records; Labour; Women
The records were donated to the Archives by Kate Braid in 1996.
All accessions have been processed as of March 2006. No further accruals are expected.
The Vancouver Women in Trades Association originally operated out of members' houses, then maintained a base in the offices of the Vancouver Status of Women organization. Upon dissolution, its records passed into the possession of one of its members, Carlyal Gittens, and subsequently to another member, Kate Braid.
Consult the inventory of the Kate Braid fonds (F 10) for additonal material on women in trades.
Some files contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Access to files marked 'restricted in whole' will be provided only through a research agreement. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- Administration, 1980 - 1987; F-9-1; 19 cm of textual records; Minutes, for all but one meeting, are lacking for the years 1982-1983.
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the administration of the organization. Activities documented include the drafting of the constitution, incorporation, annual general and monthly meetings, and staffing. Included are the constitution, drafts, minutes, correspondence, and office logbooks, as well as records relating to membership, personnel, and operating policies.
  - Correspondence 1/5, 1980 - 1982; F-9-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Correspondence 1/5, 1980 - 1982; F-9-1-0-0-1.1 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
    Restricted in whole
  - Correspondence 2/5, 1981 - 1985; F-9-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Correspondence 3/5, 1983 - 1986; F-9-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Correspondence 4/5, 1984 - 1986; F-9-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Correspondence 5/5, 1985; F-9-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Incorporation, 1982 - 1985; F-9-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Logbook 1, 1983 - 1984; F-9-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Logbook 2, 1985 - 1986; F-9-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 9-1)
  - Membership, 1984 - 1986; F-9-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Minutes of annual general meetings, 1984 - 1987; F-9-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Minutes of monthly and special meetings, 1980 - 1987; F-9-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Personnel, 1983 - 1985; F-9-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
- Finance, 1982 - 1986; F-9-2; 6 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the funding of the organization. It includes correspondence, funding proposals, worksheets and budget forecasts, and documents relating to the administration of government grants.
  - Canada Works grant, 1985 - 1986; F-9-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Challenge '85 grant, 1985 - 1986; F-9-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Funding proposals 1/2, 1982 - 1985; F-9-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
  - Funding proposals 2/2, 1983 - 1986; F-9-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-2)
- Liaison, 1980 - 1987; F-9-3; 21 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Association's work with other organizations, government agencies, and with other Women in Trades groups. Activities documented include a national conference in 1980 and participation on a number of advisory committees, among them the Advisory Committee on Training and Employment of Women (ACTEW), established by the Provincial Apprenticeship Board in 1981; the Women's Advisory Committee on Training Access (WACT), an ad hoc group formed in 1983 to lobby for revisions to the Training Access (TRAC) learning modules used by vocational institutes; the Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WETC); and the Women's Skills Development Society. Series includes correspondence, minutes, reports, briefs, newsletters and course-related materials.
  Advisory Committee on Training and Employment of Women; Women's Advisory Committee on Training Access; Women's Employment and Training Coalition; Women's Skills Development Society
  - Advisory Committee on Training and Employment of Women (ACTEW) 1/3, 1983; F-9-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Advisory Committee on Training and Employment of Women (ACTEW) 2/3, 1983 - 1986; F-9-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Advisory Committee on Training and Employment of Women (ACTEW) 3/3, 1984 - 1985; F-9-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Canada Employment and Immigration Commission (CEIC), 1984 - 1986; F-9-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Ministry of Labour, Women's Office, 1983 - 1985; F-9-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Other Women in Trades groups, 1980 - 1984; F-9-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
    Open
  - Women in Trades national conference, 1980; F-9-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Women's Advisory Committee on Training Access (WACT - TRAC) 1/3, 1983 - 1984; F-9-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 9-3)
  - Women's Advisory Committee on Training Access (WACT - TRAC) 2/3, 1984; F-9-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Women's Advisory Committee on Training Access (WACT - TRAC) 3/3, [ca 1984]; F-9-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WETC) 1/2, 1985 - 1986; F-9-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WETC) 2/2, 1985 - 1987; F-9-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Women's Skill Development Society, 1985; F-9-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
- Outreach and advocacy, 1979 - 1986; F-9-4; 25 cm of textual records 4 photographs; Physical description: 4 photographs located in F-9-4-0-7
  Series consists of records relating to the promotion of women's entry into trades occupations, gathering and dissemination of information about women and trades, and advocacy around specific cases, issues, and events, including sexual harassment and affirmative action. Activities documented include questionnaires circulated on women in trades in 1980 and 1985; speaking engagements and presentations; and an outreach project aimed at high-school students, undertaken in conjunction with the Pacific Vocational Institute and the Society of Canadian Women in Science and Technology (SCWIST) in 1984-1985. Series includes correspondence, briefs, speeches, questionnaires, graphic materials and photographs, as well as published reference materials.
  Pacific Vocational Institute; Society for Canadian Women in Science and Technology
  - Advocacy, general 1/2, 1982 - 1984; F-9-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Advocacy, general 2/2, 1982 - 1986; F-9-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Affirmative action, 1985; F-9-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-4)
  - Briefs and speeches 1/3, 1980 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - Briefs and speeches 2/3, 1981 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - Briefs and speeches 3/3, 1981 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - Graphics, 1981 - 1982; F-9-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
    Textual records; Photographic materials; Graphic materials
  - High school outreach 1/2, 1984 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - High school outreach 2/2, 1984 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - Outreach materials, 1980 - 1982; F-9-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 9-5)
  - Pratt and Whitney dismissals case, 1980 - 1982; F-9-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
    Textual records; Graphic materials
  - Presentations, 1981 - 1986; F-9-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Public relations, 1980 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Questionnaire on women in trades, 1980; F-9-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Questionnaire on women in trades, 1985; F-9-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
    Restricted in part
  - Sexual harassment, 1979 - 1985; F-9-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Speaking requests filled, 1985 - 1986; F-9-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
- Education and training, 1980 - 1986; F-9-5; 12 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Association's work documenting and promoting women's access to education and training in trades and technology. Files reflect its concerns with apprenticeships and vocational programmes; activities relating to the Pacific Vocational Institute, later reorganized as the British Columbia Institute of Technology, and the position of Women's Advocate there; and participation in seminars and public forums on training, the workplace, and women's employment opportunities. Series includes correspondence, briefs, course and program outlines, and some government publications.
  Pacific Vocational Institute; British Columbia Institute of Technology
  - Apprenticeships, 1981 - 1986; F-9-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Colleges, 1980 - 1985; F-9-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Expanding Employment Opportunities for Women seminar, 1985; F-9-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Manpower training cuts public forum, 1981 - 1982; F-9-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-6)
  - Pacific Vocational Institute 1/2, 1980 - 1982; F-9-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Pacific Vocational Institute 2/2, 1980 - 1985; F-9-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Trades courses for women, 1980 - 1985; F-9-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Women Exploring Non-Traditional Occupations (WENTO) course, Vancouver Vocational Institute, 1985 - 1986; F-9-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Women's Advocate, British Columbia Institute of Technology, 1985; F-9-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Workplace in Transition seminar, 1983 - 1984; F-9-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
- Reference files, 1976 - 1986; F-9-6; 5 cm of textual records
  Series consists of documents retained by the Association for reference purposes. It includes press clippings, publications, and compilations of resource information.
  - Media coverage 1/2, 1978 - 1986; F-9-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Media coverage 2/2, 1979 - 1985; F-9-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Publications, 1983 - 1986; F-9-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 9-7)
  - Resource information, 1976 - 1985; F-9-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 9-7)